<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<resume>
  <applicant>
    <name>Vikram Nair</name>
    <targetRole>Cyber Security</targetRole>
    <phone>+91 98123 45607</phone>
    <email>vikram.nair2024@gmail.com</email>
    <linkedin>linkedin.com/in/vikramnair-dev</linkedin>
    <github>github.com/vikramnair-dev</github>
    <location>Pune, Maharashtra</location>
  </applicant>
  <summary>Motivated B.Tech Computer Science student with a strong interest in network security, ethical hacking, and vulnerability assessment. Hands-on experience with penetration testing tools and secure coding practices. Seeking a Cyber Security Internship to contribute to real-world security operations.</summary>
  <education>
    <degree>Bachelor of Technology — Cyber Security</degree>
    <dates>2023 – 2027 (Expected)</dates>
    <school>Dr. Vishwanath Karad MIT World Peace University, Pune</school>
    <cgpa>CGPA: 8.7 / 10.0</cgpa>
    <coursework>Relevant Coursework: Network Security, Cryptography, Ethical Hacking, Digital Forensics, Operating Systems</coursework>
  </education>
  <technicalSkills>
    <skillGroup category="Languages">Python, Bash, SQL</skillGroup>
    <skillGroup category="Security Tools">Nmap, Wireshark, Burp Suite, Metasploit, OWASP ZAP</skillGroup>
    <skillGroup category="Concepts">Network Security, Vulnerability Assessment, Penetration Testing, Cryptography</skillGroup>
    <skillGroup category="Platforms">Linux, Kali Linux, Git, GitHub, AWS (basic)</skillGroup>
  </technicalSkills>
  <experience>
    <title>Cyber Security Intern — Synapse Analytics Pvt. Ltd., Pune</title>
    <dates>June 2024 – July 2024</dates>
    <bullets>
      <bullet>Performed vulnerability assessments on internal web applications, identifying 12 medium/high-risk issues.</bullet>
      <bullet>Assisted in configuring firewall and IDS rules, reducing false-positive alerts by 20%.</bullet>
      <bullet>Documented security findings and remediation steps in formal reports for the engineering team.</bullet>
    </bullets>
  </experience>
  <projects>
    <project>
      <title>Web Application Penetration Testing Lab</title>
      <stack>Burp Suite, OWASP ZAP, Python</stack>
      <dates>Jan 2024 – Mar 2024</dates>
      <bullets>
        <bullet>Set up a vulnerable web app lab and performed testing against OWASP Top 10 vulnerabilities.</bullet>
        <bullet>Identified and documented SQL injection and XSS vulnerabilities with proof-of-concept exploits.</bullet>
        <bullet>Proposed mitigations including input validation and parameterized queries.</bullet>
      </bullets>
    </project>
    <project>
      <title>Network Intrusion Detection System</title>
      <stack>Python, Scapy, Wireshark</stack>
      <dates>Sep 2023 – Nov 2023</dates>
      <bullets>
        <bullet>Built a rule-based IDS to detect port scans and ARP spoofing in real time.</bullet>
        <bullet>Achieved 90% detection accuracy on simulated attack traffic.</bullet>
      </bullets>
    </project>
    <project>
      <title>Password Strength &amp; Breach Checker Tool</title>
      <stack>Python, Hashlib, HaveIBeenPwned API</stack>
      <dates>Jul 2023 – Aug 2023</dates>
      <bullets>
        <bullet>Built a CLI tool evaluating password strength and checking for known data breaches.</bullet>
        <bullet>Used secure hashing practices to avoid storing plaintext credentials.</bullet>
      </bullets>
    </project>
  </projects>
  <certifications>
    <certification>
      <title>Google Cybersecurity Professional Certificate</title>
      <issuer>Coursera</issuer>
      <date>Completed: Aug 2023</date>
    </certification>
    <certification>
      <title>Ethical Hacking, Score: 84/100</title>
      <issuer>NPTEL (IIT Madras)</issuer>
      <date>Completed: Nov 2023</date>
    </certification>
    <certification>
      <title>Introduction to Cyber Security</title>
      <issuer>IBM / Coursera</issuer>
      <date>Completed: May 2023</date>
    </certification>
  </certifications>
  <achievements>
    <achievement>Selected among 80 students college-wide for the Smart India Hackathon (SIH 2024) internal round.</achievement>
    <achievement>Received the Academic Excellence Award for Semester 2 with the highest GPA (9.3) in the CSE department cohort of 120 students.</achievement>
    <achievement>Active contributor to two college-wide technical fests, coordinating logistics and technical sessions for 150+ participants.</achievement>
  </achievements>
  <extracurricular>
    <activity>Core Member, Technical Club, VIT Pune — organised hands-on workshops for 150+ students (2023–Present).</activity>
    <activity>Technical Blogger — published articles on Medium covering tools and best practices relevant to the field; collectively read 4,000+ times.</activity>
    <activity>Volunteer Mentor, CodeForGood (NGO Initiative) — guided 15 high school students through technology fundamentals over an 8-week programme.</activity>
  </extracurricular>
</resume>
