<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<resume>
  <applicant>
    <name>Nikhil Desai</name>
    <targetRole>Data Scientist</targetRole>
    <phone>+91 98123 45613</phone>
    <email>nikhil.desai2024@gmail.com</email>
    <linkedin>linkedin.com/in/nikhildesai-dev</linkedin>
    <github>github.com/nikhildesai-dev</github>
    <location>Pune, Maharashtra</location>
  </applicant>
  <summary>Motivated B.Tech Computer Science student with a strong analytical foundation in statistics, machine learning, and data visualization. Experienced in extracting actionable insights from complex datasets. Seeking a Data Scientist Internship to apply data-driven problem solving in a real-world setting.</summary>
  <education>
    <degree>Bachelor of Technology — Computer Science &amp; Engineering (Data Science)</degree>
    <dates>2023 – 2027 (Expected)</dates>
    <school>Vishwakarma Institute of Technology, Pune</school>
    <cgpa>CGPA: 9.0 / 10.0</cgpa>
    <coursework>Relevant Coursework: Statistics, Machine Learning, Data Visualization, Big Data Fundamentals, Linear Algebra</coursework>
  </education>
  <technicalSkills>
    <skillGroup category="Languages">Python, R, SQL</skillGroup>
    <skillGroup category="ML &amp; Stats">Scikit-learn, Statsmodels, Hypothesis Testing, Regression, Classification</skillGroup>
    <skillGroup category="Visualization &amp; Tools">Pandas, NumPy, Matplotlib, Seaborn, Power BI, Tableau</skillGroup>
    <skillGroup category="Platforms">Jupyter Notebook, Git, GitHub, Google Colab</skillGroup>
  </technicalSkills>
  <experience>
    <title>Data Science Intern — Synapse Analytics Pvt. Ltd., Pune</title>
    <dates>June 2024 – July 2024</dates>
    <bullets>
      <bullet>Built predictive models for customer churn, achieving 84% accuracy and informing retention strategy.</bullet>
      <bullet>Cleaned and analysed datasets of 50,000+ rows, identifying key drivers of business KPIs.</bullet>
      <bullet>Created interactive Power BI dashboards adopted by 3 business teams for weekly reporting.</bullet>
    </bullets>
  </experience>
  <projects>
    <project>
      <title>Customer Churn Prediction</title>
      <stack>Python, Scikit-learn, XGBoost</stack>
      <dates>Jan 2024 – Mar 2024</dates>
      <bullets>
        <bullet>Built a churn prediction model achieving 86% F1-score on imbalanced data using SMOTE.</bullet>
        <bullet>Identified top 5 churn drivers through SHAP-based feature importance analysis.</bullet>
      </bullets>
    </project>
    <project>
      <title>Sales Forecasting Dashboard</title>
      <stack>Python, Prophet, Power BI</stack>
      <dates>Sep 2023 – Nov 2023</dates>
      <bullets>
        <bullet>Built a time-series forecasting model with under 8% MAPE on monthly sales data.</bullet>
        <bullet>Designed an interactive dashboard for stakeholders to explore forecasts by region.</bullet>
      </bullets>
    </project>
    <project>
      <title>Exploratory Data Analysis on Public Health Data</title>
      <stack>Python, Pandas, Seaborn</stack>
      <dates>Jul 2023 – Aug 2023</dates>
      <bullets>
        <bullet>Conducted EDA on a 100,000-record public health dataset, surfacing 6 key correlations.</bullet>
        <bullet>Presented findings via a structured report and visualization deck.</bullet>
      </bullets>
    </project>
  </projects>
  <certifications>
    <certification>
      <title>IBM Data Science Professional Certificate</title>
      <issuer>Coursera</issuer>
      <date>Completed: Aug 2023</date>
    </certification>
    <certification>
      <title>Statistics for Data Science, Score: 87/100</title>
      <issuer>NPTEL (IIT Madras)</issuer>
      <date>Completed: Nov 2023</date>
    </certification>
    <certification>
      <title>Python for Data Science and AI</title>
      <issuer>IBM / Coursera</issuer>
      <date>Completed: May 2023</date>
    </certification>
  </certifications>
  <achievements>
    <achievement>Selected among 80 students college-wide for the Smart India Hackathon (SIH 2024) internal round.</achievement>
    <achievement>Received the Academic Excellence Award for Semester 2 with the highest GPA (9.3) in the CSE department cohort of 120 students.</achievement>
    <achievement>Active contributor to two college-wide technical fests, coordinating logistics and technical sessions for 150+ participants.</achievement>
  </achievements>
  <extracurricular>
    <activity>Core Member, Technical Club, VIT Pune — organised hands-on workshops for 150+ students (2023–Present).</activity>
    <activity>Technical Blogger — published articles on Medium covering tools and best practices relevant to the field; collectively read 4,000+ times.</activity>
    <activity>Volunteer Mentor, CodeForGood (NGO Initiative) — guided 15 high school students through technology fundamentals over an 8-week programme.</activity>
  </extracurricular>
</resume>
