<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<resume>
  <applicant>
    <name>Ananya Reddy</name>
    <targetRole>Python Developer</targetRole>
    <phone>+91 98123 45606</phone>
    <email>ananya.reddy2024@gmail.com</email>
    <linkedin>linkedin.com/in/ananyareddy-dev</linkedin>
    <github>github.com/ananyareddy-dev</github>
    <location>Pune, Maharashtra</location>
  </applicant>
  <summary>Motivated B.Tech Computer Science student with a strong command of Python for backend development, scripting, and automation. Experienced in building APIs, data pipelines, and scalable backend services. Seeking a Python Developer Internship to apply and grow these skills.</summary>
  <education>
    <degree>Bachelor of Engineering — Information Technology</degree>
    <dates>2022 – 2026 (Expected)</dates>
    <school>Sinhgad College of Engineering, Pune</school>
    <cgpa>CGPA: 8.5 / 10.0</cgpa>
    <coursework>Relevant Coursework: Backend Development, RESTful Services, Cloud Fundamentals, DBMS, Software Testing</coursework>
  </education>
  <technicalSkills>
    <skillGroup category="Languages">Python, SQL, Bash</skillGroup>
    <skillGroup category="Frameworks">Django, Flask, FastAPI</skillGroup>
    <skillGroup category="Data &amp; Tools">Pandas, NumPy, Celery, Redis</skillGroup>
    <skillGroup category="DevOps &amp; Platforms">Git, GitHub, Docker, Linux, PostgreSQL, MySQL, REST APIs</skillGroup>
  </technicalSkills>
  <experience>
    <title>Python Developer Intern — Synapse Analytics Pvt. Ltd., Pune</title>
    <dates>June 2024 – July 2024</dates>
    <bullets>
      <bullet>Developed and maintained REST APIs using Django REST Framework for an internal reporting tool.</bullet>
      <bullet>Wrote automation scripts that reduced manual data-entry workload by 40%.</bullet>
      <bullet>Optimised PostgreSQL queries, improving average response time by 25%.</bullet>
    </bullets>
  </experience>
  <projects>
    <project>
      <title>Inventory Management System</title>
      <stack>Python, Django, PostgreSQL</stack>
      <dates>Jan 2024 – Mar 2024</dates>
      <bullets>
        <bullet>Built a multi-user inventory system with role-based dashboards and stock alerts.</bullet>
        <bullet>Designed normalized database schema reducing data redundancy by 30%.</bullet>
        <bullet>Implemented automated email notifications using Celery and Redis.</bullet>
      </bullets>
    </project>
    <project>
      <title>Web Scraping &amp; Data Pipeline</title>
      <stack>Python, Scrapy, Pandas, PostgreSQL</stack>
      <dates>Sep 2023 – Nov 2023</dates>
      <bullets>
        <bullet>Built a scalable scraper collecting 50,000+ records daily from public sources.</bullet>
        <bullet>Automated cleaning and loading pipeline, cutting manual processing time by 60%.</bullet>
      </bullets>
    </project>
    <project>
      <title>URL Shortener API</title>
      <stack>Python, FastAPI, Redis</stack>
      <dates>Jul 2023 – Aug 2023</dates>
      <bullets>
        <bullet>Built a high-performance URL shortening service handling 1,000+ requests/min.</bullet>
        <bullet>Used Redis caching to reduce average response latency to under 50ms.</bullet>
      </bullets>
    </project>
  </projects>
  <certifications>
    <certification>
      <title>Python for Everybody Specialization</title>
      <issuer>Coursera</issuer>
      <date>Completed: Aug 2023</date>
    </certification>
    <certification>
      <title>Programming, Data Structures and Algorithms using Python, Score: 88/100</title>
      <issuer>NPTEL (IIT Madras)</issuer>
      <date>Completed: Nov 2023</date>
    </certification>
    <certification>
      <title>Python for Data Science and AI</title>
      <issuer>IBM / Coursera</issuer>
      <date>Completed: May 2023</date>
    </certification>
  </certifications>
  <achievements>
    <achievement>Selected among 80 students college-wide for the Smart India Hackathon (SIH 2024) internal round.</achievement>
    <achievement>Received the Academic Excellence Award for Semester 2 with the highest GPA (9.3) in the CSE department cohort of 120 students.</achievement>
    <achievement>Active contributor to two college-wide technical fests, coordinating logistics and technical sessions for 150+ participants.</achievement>
  </achievements>
  <extracurricular>
    <activity>Core Member, Technical Club, VIT Pune — organised hands-on workshops for 150+ students (2023–Present).</activity>
    <activity>Technical Blogger — published articles on Medium covering tools and best practices relevant to the field; collectively read 4,000+ times.</activity>
    <activity>Volunteer Mentor, CodeForGood (NGO Initiative) — guided 15 high school students through technology fundamentals over an 8-week programme.</activity>
  </extracurricular>
</resume>
